<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Syllabus>
    <Category>Undergrad</Category>
    <EffectiveFrom>2018</EffectiveFrom>
    <EffectiveTo>2022</EffectiveTo>
    <Semesters>
        <Semester>
            <Courses>
                <Course>
                    <Books>
                        <Book>
                            <Authors>Marvin L. Bittinger, David J. Ellenbogen and Scott A. Surgent</Authors>
                            <BookName>Calculus and its applications</BookName>
                            <Edition>10th</Edition>
                            <PublishYear>2012</PublishYear>
                            <Publisher>Pearson</Publisher>
                        </Book>
                        <Book>
                            <Authors>Ahsan Akhtar &amp; Sabiha Ahsan</Authors>
                            <BookName>Textbook of Differential Calculus</BookName>
                            <Edition>2nd</Edition>
                            <PublishYear>2009</PublishYear>
                            <Publisher>PHI</Publisher>
                        </Book>
                        <Book>
                            <Authors>N. P. Bali</Authors>
                            <BookName>Golden Co-ordinate Geometry</BookName>
                            <Edition>2nd</Edition>
                            <PublishYear>2008</PublishYear>
                            <Publisher>LUXMI</Publisher>
                        </Book>
                    </Books>
                    <ContactHours></ContactHours>
                    <CourseCode>MATH 101</CourseCode>
                    <CourseCredit>3.0</CourseCredit>
                    <CourseDescriptions>
                        <CourseDescription>
                            <Description>Definition of matrix; Different types of matrices; Algebra of matrices; Adjoint and inverse of a matrix; Elementary transformations of matrices; Matrix polynomials; Calay-Hamilton theory with uses of rank and nullity; Normal and canonical forms; Solution of linear equations; Eigenvalues and eigenvectors.</Description>
                            <Title>Matrices</Title>
                        </CourseDescription>
                        <CourseDescription>
                            <Description>Graphs and Equations: Functions and Models, Finding Domain and Range, Slope and Linear Functions, Nonlinear Functions and Models, Mathematical Modeling and Curve Fitting, Limits: A Numerical and Graphical Approach, Algebraic Limits and Continuity, Average Rates of Change, Differentiation Using Limits of, Difference Quotients, Differentiation Techniques: The Power and Sum–Difference Rules, Differentiation Techniques: The Product and Quotient Rules, The Chain Rule, Higher-Order Derivatives</Description>
                            <Title>Basic differentiation</Title>
                        </CourseDescription>
                        <CourseDescription>
                            <Description>Using First Derivatives to Find Maximum and Minimum Values and Sketch Graphs, Using Second Derivatives to Find Maximum and Minimum Values and Sketch Graphs, Graph Sketching: Asymptotes and Rational Functions, Using Derivatives to Find Absolute Maximum and Minimum Values, Maximum–Minimum Problems; Business and Economics Applications, Marginals and Differentials, Implicit Differentiation and Related Rates</Description>
                            <Title>Application of Differentiation</Title>
                        </CourseDescription>
                        <CourseDescription>
                            <Description>Exponential Functions, Logarithmic Functions, Applications: Uninhibited and Limited Growth Models, Applications: Decay, The Derivatives of and ax and logax, Economics Applications</Description>
                            <Title>Exponential and logarithmic Differentiation</Title>
                        </CourseDescription>
                        <CourseDescription>
                            <Description>Change of axes: transformation of coordinates. Simplification of equations of the curves. Pair of straight lines: Homogeneous second degree equations. Conditions for general second degree equations to represent a pair of straight lines. Angle between the lines. Pair of straight lines joining the origin to the points of intersection of the curve and a line.</Description>
                            <Title>2D Co-ordinate Geometry-1</Title>
                        </CourseDescription>
                        <CourseDescription>
                            <Description>Circles and system of circles: Tangents and normals. Pair of tangents. Chord of contact. Orthogonal circles. Radical axis and its properties. Parametric coordinates</Description>
                            <Title>2D Co-ordinate Geometry-2</Title>
                        </CourseDescription>
                        <CourseDescription>
                            <Description>Rectangular coordinates. Direction cosines and angle between two lines. The plane and the straight lines. The equation of a sphere. The standard forms of equations of the central conicoids, cones and cylinders.</Description>
                            <Title>3D Co-ordinate Geometry</Title>
                        </CourseDescription>
                    </CourseDescriptions>
                    <CourseObjectives>
                        <CourseObjective>
                            <Objective>To learn about matrix, determinant and its application to the solution of systems of linear equations.</Objective>
                        </CourseObjective>
                        <CourseObjective>
                            <Objective>To analyze functions and their graphs. It will be shown how calculus and graphing utilities, working together, can provide most of the important information about their behavior of functions.</Objective>
                        </CourseObjective>
                        <CourseObjective>
                            <Objective>To provide students with a good understanding of the concepts two dimensional geometry.</Objective>
                        </CourseObjective>
                        <CourseObjective>
                            <Objective>To Students will learn about co-ordinate, translation and rotation of axis, conic, conic section for two dimension</Objective>
                        </CourseObjective>
                        <CourseObjective>
                            <Objective>To learn about two/ three dimensional co-ordinate, conicoid i.e. sphere, cone, cylinder, parpabolid, ellipsoid, hyperboid</Objective>
                        </CourseObjective>
                    </CourseObjectives>
                    <CourseTitle>Mathematics I (Matrix, Differential Calculus and Coordinate Geometry)</CourseTitle>
                    <CourseType>Theory</CourseType>
                    <LaboratoryRequirements/>
                    <LearningOutcomes>
                        <LearningOutcome>
                            <Outcome>Use matrix to the solution of systems of linear equations.</Outcome>
                        </LearningOutcome>
                        <LearningOutcome>
                            <Outcome>Analyze functions and their graphs and how calculus and graphing utilities, working together, can provide most of the important information about their behavior of functions</Outcome>
                        </LearningOutcome>
                        <LearningOutcome>
                            <Outcome>Understand co-ordinate and its translation and rotation, point, line, mid-point, distance and vector in two-dimensional space</Outcome>
                        </LearningOutcome>
                        <LearningOutcome>
                            <Outcome>Solve two/ three dimensional co-ordinate, conicoid i.e. sphere, cone, cylinder, parpabolid, ellipsoid, hyperboid problems</Outcome>
                        </LearningOutcome>
                    </LearningOutcomes>
                    <Prerequisite></Prerequisite>
                    <Rationale></Rationale>
                </Course>
                <Course>
                    <Books/>
                    <ContactHours>0</ContactHours>
                    <CourseCode>ENG 103</CourseCode>
                    <CourseCredit>3.0</CourseCredit>
                    <CourseDescriptions/>
                    <CourseObjectives/>
                    <CourseTitle>Communicative English</CourseTitle>
                    <CourseType>Theory</CourseType>
                    <LaboratoryRequirements/>
                    <LearningOutcomes/>
                    <Prerequisite>None</Prerequisite>
                    <Rationale></Rationale>
                </Course>
            </Courses>
            <SemesterName>Semester 1</SemesterName>
        </Semester>
    </Semesters>
</Syllabus>
